hello thanks for joining me again
so I will give it a little context for
Andrew my conversation here with Andrew
Taggard but before that I just want to
let you know that there's a circling
Institute my company we're doing all of
our courses online right now so please
feel free to to join us the links below
if you want to get the information about
the drop in events like the three hour
drop in events that we do every Thursday
online you can do that through the
Facebook link and I think that's below
if you're interested in discussing
working with me 101 my emails below just
email me I take I'm a little bit slow
with email something about the
coronavirus and communications is really
strange she'd think I did well I've
never been able to manage that but
anyways email me and I will I will get
back with you and I think that's it
so Andrew Taggart at delightful
conversation as he said in an email
afterwards a real purity to the
conversation I really felt that he's uh
andrew is my understanding because we
didn't get much into the content of his
life but rather rather I would say
we discovered what we both lived it in a
felt way and I walked I walked away
feeling as though I could feel like a
chant going through my body almost like
a like an implicit sense of
openness being a fullness it was really
great and a great example I think of of
dialo goes with a with a explicitly
mystical element to it and I really
enjoyed talking with him about that and
also his work he's a lot of his work
that he's been working on is has to do
with something called total work and
he's a philosopher and so he has been
doing on his blogs and I'll put all the
links and stuff below on his blogs he's
been working out a lot of his thinking
around he say our relationship to work
but from a very deep level and even it's
it's kind of it's it's such a a level
that
the mistakes of understanding what he's
talking about reveals the thing that
he's talking about right that level so
um yeah I hope you enjoy it
and
great weekend thank you everyone who
just came on we we just its morning time
as you can see the light coming and I
may have to move at a certain point cuz
they normally don't talk this early but
um I can hinder birdsong okay
yeah so far we've just covered
everything from the Midwest it's a good
gorian chance to acoustical sound
enculturation and how-how-how chanting
kind of becomes itself as a kind of
acculturation and then I was just we
were just talking about something that I
that caught me that he would just kind
of said I think without thinking about
it you said yeah oh yeah normally when
I'm philosophy philosophizing throughout
the day right
the the and I think the thing that
struck me is the apparent ordinariness
of that right and just that you just
said it like that like oh yeah just like
you'd normally when I'm sweet being or
it is like so yeah and I have a feeling
I'm feeling that statement just that
just the way that that is rolled off
without really thinking about it um peak
is a peak into your world which is your
world has been so I've listened tea I've
listened to your conversations with you
Hannes and I listen to one with them the
the the monk guy who has the podcast
what's his name again
oh okay no Thurston yeah and you in that
one you really went into philosophical
inquiry and dialogue and done your
ticket you really beautifully
articulated
think what you do my impression was is
what you do when you see clients right
and have philosophical conversations
with them in the way that you unfolded
that was so I kid
he was so moving to me and it was in it
it I had this experience of one relating
to it a lot however the way that you put
it at the end at the end of you
describing philosophical dialogue I
found myself in a very clear clean crisp
almost structure being held by the
structure that was very very pure and
moving and rich so I'm just interested
in who this being is over here okay I'm
just sweeping man I'm just sweeping is
there something you'd like to know yeah
like so for example when you say
philosophizing throughout the day um
what do you mean what does that mean to
you what is it it's a very deep
heartfelt inquiry into the nature of
wisdom of what it is to lead a wise life
there's you know I'm almost crying right
now there's a sweetness about it that
just can't be subtracted
from the inquiry of the investigation of
course it happens between me and myself
some philosophers of antiquity who said
that philosophizing is dialoguing with
oneself to be sure but above all it
happens with other people we should
really think of it as if it were art
performance because that's the closest
analogue I can provide here think of a
some kind of play in which someone it's
it's dark - people don't know each other
perhaps they can't even see each other
there are only the voices available only
the voices emerging out of the darkness
all they know is that one person has
gently agreed to play the role of
someone who's asking
one sinuous question and the other
person know is that she has taken on the
role of providing one muddled or a clear
answer but in any case an earnest answer
and through this very simple form
[Music]
there's a what arises is something that
is like a third or I want to say the
word of understanding here but I don't
want to mislead either because the
understanding is a deeply felt something
so it's a understanding that gets at the
heart of the matter at the same time
that comes from the heart where the
heart mind is a unified Faculty of sorts
the unified Faculty there's a way yes
yes it's not we don't I don't want to be
I don't I hope it's clear that it's not
just talking about the nature of truth
that's fine if someone wanted to do that
but it's also not just feeling our way
into the dark there's a unified form of
feeling knowing
that arises in and through the form and
that shows that there is Robbie toss
wouldn't the other conversation I so
that's a matter of an existential weight
and then there's a newt and newfound
clarity for both of us it's as if we're
seeing don't change metaphors as if
we're hearing the same thing which is on
a thing at the same time together yes so
I can I can only the best way of like is
it it's a bit like it's a it's a it's a
mystical form because the the language
becomes an instrument almost like a
musical instrument in the service of the
perfume of silence the perfume of
knowing silence hmm that's disclosed hmm
now the person afterward you better if
it's early conversations might say well
that was wonderfully conceptually clear
and then there will be notes or
something like that which will make it
seem as if it was highly discursive but
over time it becomes more and more
abundantly clear that no no no that
wasn't quite it what was it was the
perfume of silence or stillness that
revealed it's always already having been
here yeah yes
so Holies already having been here yeah
I really appreciate the one as you're
describing it there's a way where we're
in hearing you and in understanding you
it's almost
what it takes to understand what you're
saying is to is also an instruction like
my mind has to or my awareness or
discursiveness has to do the thing that
you're saying in order to understand
what you're saying where the what you're
talking about is what I'm doing in
understanding what you're talking about
it's an invitation to sink into the
stillness of being in invitation mm-hmm
language is a language of this sort is
an invitation to sink and it's still in
stillness of being hmm philosophy and
it's hard as a meditation that unwinds
two people together or at least two
people together and reveals to them that
which they had unfortunately either to
overlooked but now they're but now they
see very clearly the thing that's the
note the thing you know you keep money
you had just come from listening to
glory and shams
yes that's it's already altered my
disposition and the opening part of our
conversation today yeah I'd just get
this I really I can feel that I can feel
that in the intimacy that feels of vocht
because there is something about sound
and listening that is very unified with
itself right like in carrying about it
right so as you're talking about it I
just do it's it's I feel I feel a tone
no joke and say what's the difference
you and I are chanting right now right
both of us are obviously used to using
our voices mm-hmm me you can tell from
the particular resonant quality of the
sound right now
as I had some and some Johnny Cash or
some such to it you can you can feel it
that there's already the conversation or
every right now is already so to speak
chanting and I'm thinking about just the
way you Hannes describes you is a
philosopher mystic and I the impression
I'm getting is is when I think I'm
getting it what do you mean right and I
think what he means is this sense where
it's I mean oftentimes when people think
of philosophy or a have a philosophical
conversation there's there's a one a in
which the thing that's talked about is
connected over there and then people
talk about their thoughts about it but
there's a way in which thing we're
talking about it what the sense I get
with you is that the very talking about
it is is voguing something almost it's
already there right and that in some way
that felt that a little bit right a
thoughtful resonance of it is I don't
know if it is the right word but the
point
yes that's right gonna see the intimacy
is precisely the point
yeah if you if you discard the intimacy
then you discard the very heart or
spirit of philosophy as I understand it
right so remember of philosophy has a
comes from a very venerable background I
I
I think it's much closer to religion and
spirituality than it is to silence yeah
so and there and if that's true namely
but it's closer to religion spirituality
and then all of them are to use your
word sort of circling around mm-hmm the
ineffable philosophy becomes
contemplative philosophy in particular
with the kind of it I'm engaged in is is
it just mm-hmm
letting us apprehend yeah either via via
negativa but by slowly getting rid of
conceptual or discursive mind or maybe
positively it can use language to
results to lift up but in either case
I'm not saying that every one of them
are speaking is is is articulating the
matter in this way but it's unnecessary
to do so it's that he or she gets that
something happened which was not really
happening yeah why else come back why
else keep philosophizing yeah one second
and philosophizing i think my life isn't
realizing that she's having her meeting
in the kitchen right next door hang on a
second
of course so it's all one small sweeping
good yes totally yeah yeah you have a
family right I have a wife
yeah yeah yeah in in do you have
children we didn't have children yet no
I thought I had this impression yet
children right yeah yeah yeah yeah I
have a 17 year old son okay yeah yeah I
just get the sense of um well the myth
mystical element like well not even that
element this this this sense in which
you evoke and there's a way in my own
way that I have really really really
really relate to this right like I think
it's it's uh well it's here right now
yeah yeah yeah what is that what is the
here that's right now for you
the it's here for us yes it's it's like
the what had been in the background
Aaron really years starts to reveal
itself as the foreground it's the moment
you realize that there is it always has
been the ocean on which you've been
floating yeah and that's a little bit
too separate even it's not even that
you're just floating on the ocean you
were gently submerged in the ocean but I
I feel it was a kind of presence maybe I
should put it a little bit less
metaphorically would show there's a
presence I'll give you an example of it
I'm I really felt it my wife and I sand
years ago were at a Buddhist monastery
in Southern California it was a very
small one and we went up before the day
of practice into the hillsides and I
could just feel that the silence itself
was full and it wasn't anything
particular about the place it's not as
many fetish I didn't say here is
fullness but it was right yeah it was
clear that's where it was Southern
California obviously but then there are
times
that that initial pull something which
is not a thing is is the presence that's
here between us among us through us
around us and you can feel it when the
word feels a little bit clumsy here of
course so it was the word sense that's
clumsy too but and any any any word any
any any feeling or sense word you try to
use to describe it as it isn't quite
accurate but draw all that you know it
and so it I guess it's you know if we
want to be a little internet we could
say it's love mmm-hmm yeah that would be
fine too yeah and there is something
about there seems like it seems like
that there's something I there's
something about the ocean it's really
interesting to me it's kind of it's
always has this once I've had this
experience every time I meditate right
where like especially if I'm
particularly uncensored or something
right now particularly not in the ocean
when I sit down and I have some sense of
like ocean and I think when I think
ocean like like at the time that I'm
thinking ocean I'm thinking that I'm
actually thinking about the thing that
I'm representing in my mind I usually
always have this feeling when the bat
that background becomes the foreground
there's this recognition it's this sense
of oh like somehow remember when I was
thinking about this I thought I was
thinking about this but known it's that
I this in some sense is not the rips
representation of this and there's this
quality for me
no matter how much I know that it's
always are like oh yeah the trick
there's a surprise yeah yeah delicious
surprise yeah it's as if you have a
dirty no is it - speaking platonic
language it's is this it's as if you had
forgotten and now are remembering your
true home oh it's a slapstick surprise
that oh here it is again and again by
again I mean it hasn't ever left I just
went off on a little journey and I seem
to have become poor III believe that I'd
forgotten yeah it was always already
here all along yeah yeah yeah and
there's a quality of the Forgotten s hmm
right or the believing of forgotten is
it's not even that explicit it seems to
be part it's it's from The Forgotten
plates the state of Forgotten as' right
it's not like I'm thinking about that
I'm representing it but when it's when
it comes into the foreground or it
reveals it's none back or its background
and foreground it is whatever you call
that that that sense of emergence that
sense of abiding and yes remembering
there's this quality of coz it doesn't
feel like a it doesn't feel like a
discovery doesn't feel like something
what's absent and I didn't have never
seen before in in foments there it's not
that it's almost like a member in that's
right I may have forgotten for 35 years
but it was just like I was just a little
bit left
yeah right is notice that that that
sense of it
it seems to be part of the quality of it
that no matter how much I meditate no
matter how much I have that still fresh
it's still fresh every time in its
instant yeah that seems revealing of it
mm-hmm yeah okay that's a fresh
revealing of itself yeah and so and
there's also quality you know and this
really kind of links to a lot of the
conversations that I've been having
about conversation right um and about
you know what Vicki and I are in kind of
constant dialogue about right either on
text or any conversations this inquiry
about dia logos right at that moment
where you know when my understanding is
there's dialectic which is in a certain
sense it's like taking propositions and
you as as almost like logs on a fire
mm-hmm gathering right you gathered the
logs and then you start into dialectic
where you start to a dialogue about in
these since the propositions and at a
certain point the dialogue emerges into
dialogue oh s--- in a catches flame and
it both lights and transcends what's
what's lit but also reveals the faces of
everybody right end this kinship with
the logos and there's a quality that's
been that it has become more apparent to
me as of late that part of the
remembrance seems to have an equality of
affinity that is also aspirational and
it
the word logos this kind of sense of the
of in philosophical conversation a and a
tuning to a remembrance of and an
aspirational quality of something like
the gathering of the logos and I think
I'm just appreciating my experience of
you right now and of us right now given
the background in those conversations
that I've been because part of what part
of part of the I think the tailless of
those conversations is
having that sense of one wanting to
reawaken that you know in the in in the
sense of the original sense of
philosophy of my understanding was a
philosophy as a way of life right that
it's not just it's not just the
propositions right but the but the
propositions as as in play and that and
that in the playing of them in the act
over the event of philosophy if you will
that that when one engages in it one
becomes someone who could engage in it
which is aid kind of a transformation
and I'm really I really get that the
gravity of that is we're talking I'm
just appreciating it so it's like on one
level there's all these conversations
I've been having about this and then
having that show up and shine forth in
you with all those things it's just
really I'm just noticing a lot of a lot
of things that are gathering themselves
up the logos mm-hmm there's a just a
just a shining presence everything is
everything I experience philosophies
it's somewhat pedestrian terms
everything is okay and isn't this
wonderful
isn't this wonderful that we're here
philosophizing this is the wonderful
right now and and and that's not in some
kind of Chloe or sentimental way it's
just just just wonderful to ask a
question it's wonderful this for this
question to arrive right here isn't it
isn't it isn't it just glorious that
it's just placed here for us and that
sense is a true gift and how wonderful
that someone else can not even consider
it but allow the question to be
something that
steeps yes it's nothing quick to
and four but it kind of moles but it it
Trent Trent marries and transforms on
kind of transforms the question it's
taken up taken in and the more that
someone does this the more it's not even
interviewing the more that it happens
the more it just becomes clear that
everything is just really wonderful in
and I don't mean to say that we're not
middle of the coronavirus to be sure I'm
talking about they could have met a
physical tenor of philosophizing I'm not
speaking about the political conditions
we find ourselves in yeah
I just mean somehow it becomes clear
that everything is really just just just
sweet wonderful uni the sense is always
beyond the verge of tears no matter how
dark or how light the topic is exquisite
[Music]
the a and I'm I think I think sometimes
about this a lot about you know cut
there's conversations about I'm looking
in a mirror like I can spend about
eternity talking about the things
reflected in the mirror yet the the one
thing that the mirror can't reflect is
the mirror it's the only thing going on
on some level but it's something that
can't be reflected so they're in some on
some level like I feel like when you
talk about the okayness what I give
present is that the shining forth of the
thing that Kant is non-representational
right mom but is
imminent within all the representations
it shines forth and so no matter yes
reflected there is something there and
that there's something like philosophy
ah hmm
right that is you could say is like a
somehow
points to right points to but also it
was a feeling way right yes well it's
it's all better each each philosophical
question there's a con
each philosophical question can be
answered by the finite or discursive
mind
but not well enough mm-hmm so we ask
ourselves where does the question come
from we don't know it comes from mystery
well we took where does the question
come from you know that's from
meditation but the same is true of
philosophy where does the question
arrive from what is the substance what
what is a substratum of every question
what is it that it's what is it that
it's pointing toward what is it or does
it go this question and above all what
is it about a philosophical question
that is not just about how are you it as
Joseph Pieper once put it
each philosophic question invokes God in
the world which is another somewhat
metaphorical way of trying to say what
you are just saying
mmm each philosophical question
[Music]
is-is-is is itself and of course is not
itself it is itself it is itself the
question are you afraid of death that's
a philosophical question and there's a
specifiable answer that question are you
afraid of death is calling forth
everything it leaves nothing out it
can't leave anything up it's it's that
plentiful and glorious generous hmm
there's a quality of
[Music]
consents in the I'm listening to you my
sense is the word the word divine comes
to mind right in and I think I hear it
echoing when you talk about essentially
philosophy and religion right are are
somehow closer to each other then say
philosophy and science right did this
there's a quality in Europe I also felt
it when you were talking about the
chanting the christian mystic chanting
yeah the divine the videos right yes
[Music]
there's an orientation right around that
is very very uh I would say in our in
our particular time right now if there's
an orientation that makes less and less
sense to most people it's that right I
know it's not it's like just just
remember Plato if it makes less of a
sense to people that it might be true
yes we should admit the upside-down
quality of philosophy on what Sophia I
don't know I felt this smile start from
your toes was dental it
yeah yeah yeah okay it gave me a set up
story gave me a shut up outrageous
and that quite that sensitive de body
right you know it I can we can say a
word like sacred something sacred right
and then if we say that the divine the
divinity shines the fourth is the
sacredness is present their varied they
they feel very very similar tones but
they're not the same tone no tea does
that make sense to you I think we've
been become more okay with the word
sacred once a while and like modernity
but it feels a little bit over there
whereas the Divine in particular in the
way that you're using it right now
that's full mouth full bodied full
reality yeah I've been using the word
sweetness a lot recently and perhaps
overly much but the divine has as a
feeling of sweetness about it for me
mmm everything's mmm mmm the tree is
sweet the bird is sweet the bird song I
can hear that sweet the sunshine with
sunlight on your face is sweet
perhaps even the distant sound of your
your wife's voice sweet or the
pitter-patter of mine my wife's
footsteps not again this week yeah so
there's a there's a there's a whole line
from James Joyce's Ulysses in which
Stephen Dedalus is out of school this is
their kids playing outside and and
someone says well what's that he says
what's that mystery says that's gone he
wasn't being probably being pyretic all
that time and I'm not saying who's being
a pantheist I'm not taking a view at all
right now I'm just talking about
experience I'm not taking about
modernism or non-duality at the moment
just saying the experience is that of
sweet divinity of being
[Music]
when you say sweetness and I think of
taste mmm tasting something hmm is it
there's something there's something
similar to hearing sound and taste that
have a very similar quality to them and
in their immediacy of bringing so much
together at once in its immediacy the
sound has this quality of it seems to
announce distance mm I it's on some
level but as right here like and there's
something about taste that oh yeah it's
almost a little bit I would imagine it's
a little bit reversed right it's but
this the same thing work it announces
immediacy but totality like the taste of
something right yes that's one closes
one's eyes that one just listens one
realizes that the sound of the voices
it's always already here right now
there's a vibrant vibrating pulsating
hereness there's nowhere else that the
sound is heard one can put that I fight
to fend off this language by saying that
the sound sound is always appearing to
the witness at a certain level of
understanding hmm it's always here
appearing to the witness hmm it a gone
there's no separation between there
there is no sound really there's just
the arising hearing appearing to
witnessing consciousness hmm so it fills
Evia but this is sound therefore from
from the proper point of view it is
hearing a rising one can you even speak
it but because it sounds as if it could
be a representation but it's not it's
just hearing rising vibratory hearing
arising - witnessing consciousness and
everything is just filled up with it and
the same the close our eyes and quit
taste it's
in me if we give ourselves over to it
it's it's it's immediate and perhaps
even use the word sweetness is not meant
to be like sugar eNOS it's meant to say
that everything is everything tastes
wonderful and if somehow the immediacy
is also include so many horizons mm-hmm
right in its immediately and it's all
months no right it's all at once that's
an immediate see yeah
mmm and then I'm noticing too with what
strikes a strong note and when you say
you say when one thinks of I or when
when one tastes he could have said when
I taste or when I he said one in it and
it seemed to tune to what you're talking
about
what is that what is that when we'll say
one one tastes one I think my if I were
to say my experience of it is where
something like we could save this one we
could say this one use this one there's
something there's an eligibility of
their that like I just can just noticed
I'm it's a indentation it's an
invitation to anyone ya know in some
cases with like some cases if your
philosophizing you in your every animal
political sort you say one feels right
now a little bit sack or something like
I've heard that many times you know
that's the kind of dissociation so
that's not hopefully what it meant I
meant when one case I mean anyone any
one of us you say should you I but any
of us please please please please taste
put please here please close your eyes
yeah isn't intent and and and and it's
an intent it's an internet one because
one what one will discover that if one
closes one's eyes and listens that the
luminous witness is attuned to the the
arising hearing and the falling away of
hearing yes
it's very intimate there's not a hair
breaths of separation between the
hearing and the witnessing mmm except
post facto mm-hmm I also like it cuz I
can
definitely count that high Justin math
skills yes you won't be helping your 17
year old son therefore with those I'm
not outside yes you know one of the one
of the things I've heard you you and
Jonathan talk about and in your other
conversations too seems you've given a
lot of thought right to modernity and in
particularly humanism and it's
interesting and also the work that
you've done around which I've really
enjoyed getting um mostly in the wave it
has me thinking getting it right there's
an intimacy in it it actually reveals
the non intimacy of the time I'm in but
in that doing it reveals something which
is the your work your work around work
right about the totalizing
the sense of total like not everything
that's instant deepening that seems to
get in the way of this conversation
right now for most people that's after
total work is just the arguments but
total work or everything to do with
whatever would get in the way of this
commerce people have this conversation
right now yeah yeah and everything is a
gross over over century it is
exaggeration but many things you know
get in the way this commerce rate sure
good you know yeah
additional possibility for conversations
like these he has the intelligibility of
them of the equity of them of the
obvious nough skeins of intimacy I'm I'm
I'm worried about everything almost
everything that gets in the way of
what's happening right here right now
and that although you correct yourself
when you say everything there's a
there's a there's something though that
you're also evoke
or revealing when you say everything hmm
because what I sense and what I've
appreciated about when you've talked
about it is that it's not in Heidegger
language it's not you're not talking
about the antic sense of oh there's me
and then there's something I do call the
work I think what you're saying is no on
a almost like a pre reflective level
I already always view myself as a worker
right
and therefore constitute a world that
occurs to me as working or not working
right and that it's a it's like a a deep
organizing structure if you will mm-hmm
that isn't something I do therefore like
even you know it's kind of funny to
think about this but the distinct you'll
work-life balance and your connection in
in your connection with a lot of the
conditions of that and how that's gotten
so deep in our ontological understanding
of being right the way that we don't
even explicate so it's like appreciate
like the way that you talk about it to
explicate and bring from a background to
a foreground in that sense right that's
where it's been impactful for me and
listening to you right is it's revealing
of being right in that way and it's
funny it's it's revealing in the sense
of like the moment I kind of you know my
dad used to say he's he's been sober for
he's been sober in a in the AAA world
from ICONic 35 years or something like
that so he has he's really great
like I'm per speaker phrases because
he's like yeah I saw the sudden flash of
life like the moment I popped my head on
out of my ass your father sounds like ah
go Chicago in yeah there's a there's a
connection and I've appreciated you have
a very it seems to give it a lot of
thought of that that would
locates of this the notion of humanism
mm-hmm right and in it in it in a way
that hasn't quite heard that described
as you've described it before yeah I
would just love to hear and it's
interesting to have that as the the
sense of the conversation that we read
right and and having that really be
present with with us
and then you'd you're like whatever gets
in the way this is what I'm talking
about yeah yeah yeah let's consider
humanism the ordinary definition is that
man is the measure of all things I've
tried to suggest a lot of things have
been drawn from since we're using high
daguerreian language kind of it what it
is to be in the world and the the two
that had withdrawn or Theo's or a notion
of divinity the Gregorian chant any any
notion of higher that's extraordinarily
important for us extraordinarily
important it's withdrawn because it
doesn't enable a hierarchy of values
yeah any any genuine discussions of the
goodbye free day Minya become a highly
subjective in nature was the first one
with feyo's withdrawals in the second
relatedly is that cosmos withdraws that
there could be an intelligible beautiful
well organized order in which all of us
find ourselves and to which we all
belong as up and vanished and we don't
even and in both cases we don't know
quite that they both vanished
we've already always already come on the
scene too late then the cat-burglar
already came many many decades prior and
we're we were living we were living on
the scene now not knowing that's the
Kings so what would what emerges
concomitant with the disappearance of
divine the cosmos is humanism the the
view according to which man is the
measure of all things and I find it hard
still to describe this I find it hard
still today but it really is as if we've
walked or been born or been thrown into
a world where everything is just
drenched in drenched in human thoughts
and human feelings and human sensations
and human concerns and human
technologies and human platforms and
human endeavors and human projects and
they're all of such central organizing
importance that we couldn't possibly get
behind them a good simple example to
help out an area rich would be social
media how is it possible for there to be
such sweaty interest you know kind of
sweat proud interest in in social media
in many cases people talk usually it's
some kind of level of dopamine hits and
things like that but I'm talking about
things that are more basic how do you
how does this social media platform ever
emerge in the first place and become
tantalizing
[Music]
it's only that visa the other human
beeings begins which I measure myself
and with which I understand myself this
is a this is an entirely new as I try to
say about total worth is an
extraordinary extraordinarily new
experiment that we didn't realize that
we're involved in yeah I don't feel I'm
not know if any other culture that has
not had different forms of being apart
from human beings against which we
understood herself for example we you
might think about some kind of hierarchy
of being or the great chain of being you
have God angels who are complete
intelligence beings other animals
vegetable life rocks and so forth we
don't I'm not subscribing to the
Christian and being I'm just telling you
that you have a way of understanding the
human as being situated yeah as having a
proper place of being in right relation
use that term with all of their beings
please please don't mistake I'm not
trying to romanticize this one I'm just
saying that the structure is a humbling
structure it's a it's a it's an
ontological eating as opposed to simply
at the cementery humbling structure yeah
yeah it's the condition of possibly for
reverence yeah and and compassion for
all sentient beings and and so forth
yeah so in the intimacy we experience in
this conversation is only possible on
the grounds that we don't think it's
just about two human beings here that's
lovely that there are but our
conversation has unfolded the these
sentient beings within something
indescribable
I'm sinking into what you just said
about in some way how I heard what you
said anyone is was the absorption of
social media and the and the sweating
interest yeah exemplify is something
that highlights
yeah way to make that man is the measure
of all things ladies got this sense of
like because there is that quality with
social media and technology in general
that just brings everything into this
and particularly without a relation ship
to that which it's in a relationship
with right it's like that's part of what
it seems to do is thus the absorbing
quality is the more you look at it the
more you don't notice that you're
looking at it right the more interest
like the
the sense of withdrawal doesn't it it
conceals what it's concealed right
whereas what you're talking about with
the the sense of hierarchy and how I
really like to work how you said it
sense of op divine prey and being
situated and when I how I heard that is
not like as you as you made sure to to
to exemplify that you weren't you're not
talking about something conceptual
you're talking about it's more like
situated in the way a hot stove when you
touch it situates you right it's like
there's no that doesn't this isn't
that's not a reflective act that you're
proposing it's no in that moment you
you're right size to that every teacher
way to you great and that there's
something about social media that will
almost kind of levels everything off
right and yeah you right it um that
sense of being inside of something
bigger does not like yeah you're right
it completely it's in framed right you
becoming framed yeah there's a lot of
talk today about focusing being focused
I might joke what we really needed is to
be absolutely unfocused we needed her
learning how to relax the focus to to
learn how to take our our clenched fists
off hmm meditate meditation Zen master
token says as peace itself
meditation is the beings breathing
itself through this particular vessel
but for that to be so for that to be
tasted as as such there has to be
defocusing de efforting anand framing
unclenching contemplation and the proper
sense is just actually apprehending
luminosity before all of the
contractions we good yeah I'm hearing
the play of the precision of the word
apprehend right versus comprehend mm-hmm
yeah that's really telling there's a you
know it's funny
well this though as I understand but
check this juxtaposition between this
hyper concern right with focusing right
so interesting because I just felt the
hijacking of I'm I I that's given by
that whole structure right and the sense
in which I think I want to focus but I
really got the sense of the I that I
call I mmm
right isn't the eye that apprehends and
I was just in the night I as you're
talking I had the sense of just this
position of focusing and then going
telling that person now focus on all
that is and then just watching it right
there in it
sense of like there's that immediate
that right sighs that that that the
sense of what I can't see what I can't
smell what I can't I can't get ahold of
it right but and I I think it's an act
of love
yeah that right there you describe
that's love yeah yeah the the ER there
for someone and makes me just just just
a be with and abide with everything's
before let it or not been focused on
that's an act of love so it's really
well right I want to I want to kind of
stay with that for a second so there's I
never quite saw it like that the sense
of just if I take that sense of focusing
and I just go okay now focus on all of
it there's an obvious Ness that
immediately I become I feel myself
within that mmm a great size yeah yeah
and there's a way that that is what's
interesting about that because I imagine
like you have the gamer or something
burn in that in the talking to all of
his friends and I've I've actually
worked with families or I'll go and I'll
go and how I work with them is I'll go
and just plant myself in the family for
a couple of weeks and work with the
family as a families which is I've
learned more about the human condition I
think in doing that work
[Music]
I've really noticed and I've gotten a
view into what it is to be a teenager in
many cases now hmm is where there are so
many kids that I've worked with that
that they would go to school right and
they wouldn't talk to any of their
friends at school
but they would come home again on the
video game and have this intense
relationship with them online right and
like literally literally from everything
in their in their pre reflective
responses what was real was that right
was the online world what was
inconsequential and not real
based on their lack of responsiveness to
it was everything outside of that hmm
right and so I I think I just felt this
I just made a connection and what you're
talking about
I'm like what I think about like okay
let's just tell him to relax and there's
learnings I've appreciated about your
work right and I can feel the
sensibility in just this conversation
right
is that what I think I experience you
evoke ik in talking about this right is
that there's a way in which to
understand what you're saying actually
is to come into contact right which
isn't a triangle relax from within the
frame but there is something that just
happens when you touch you touch
everything that that is withdrawn and is
with it's withdrawn misses withdrawn
right and that sense of withdrawn the
only appropriate response is a kind of a
relaxation to even get it right yes yes
that even the relaxation isn't something
I'm doing the relaxation is just what
happens is a human being as they open to
all of it relaxation is the
understanding the deepest sense thanks
for hanging with me says take a walk
through that it's really nice because I
had them and is having me make sense a
little bit of this thing that I just
started doing spontaneously a couple
years ago when I go on walks where well
oh I walk and I'll I'll just bring my
attention to them to the place in which
I can't see anymore
and there's something about walking
because there's a movement you can kind
of highlight that place and to watch the
the process of doing that right because
just the act of trying to do that and my
periphery as I'm walking my first
instinct is to focus on it but the
moment you focus on it it's the moment
that you lose the other one then you
lose the other one but as you kind of
engage I noticed it as I engage with
that there is what it is to focus is
exactly what it is to relax right
there's this
a very concrete way which kind of gets
at that I just noticed myself kind of
doing that spontaneously and have had
lots of thoughts about who am i doing
when I focus right what in it and then
there is a quality of that relaxation
every time I would go to effort starts
to shift over and to like
effort is now to focus is to relax
that's the Taoist and sent that is the
understanding didn't need a step one see
that you're always see that you whoever
the US here is always involved effortful
focusing I'm straining to understand
something I think it's a hard problem to
solve I really need to to act considered
Li bring this about and so forth hmm I'm
a Protestant in terms of my work ethic
visiter of everything that seems so step
one you start to realize that you sort
of realize that it shows up in your
constructiveness and various ways step
to make a distinction
oh I've had I finally had an experience
walking one day I was this is kind of a
common one from William James just the
variety is a religious experience you
find these people were really just
trying to get somewhere and they finally
at wit's end say I can't do it I call it
surrender or a true letting go and lo
and behold there's a genuine relaxation
so stuck - I actually taste relaxation
but relaxation
there's a word that we should use
appropriately or it doesn't mean non
energetic harder just lying around as
you describe the relaxation is full and
beautiful and seamless it's sinewy
although it's smooth like a calligraphic
brush stroke come on Zen master so step
two you realize that and then of course
you get attachments if you start kids
realize that's very nice
so you know the ultimate Andalus I was
like oh there's really no difference
between focusing and a proper sense and
relaxation because everything at a
deeper level is always already
relaxation stones being silenced being
is being is already
but a little yes yes that's right so
it's it's it's already it's already the
Dow that can be told is not the eternal
down the Dow is is already smooth and
liquid even to call it that is to call
too much of course so focusing out of
from the place of in continuity with
relaxation is itself relaxed and when
there is no focusing there's just the
seeking back into being qua being there
just it's just exhalations and
inhalations in the third step it's just
everything is everything is smooth your
wife has me any other room and it's it's
it's fine you just say you say you
didn't contribute inquire on I'm having
a conversation someone you started
talking to me about Gregorian chants
being at the intersection and she begets
it because she gets you at this point
I'm sure yeah totally she totaled work
yes is like it's funny I felt like kind
of just bringing that back in just feel
just a comment best of that right yes
exactly is precisely it seems to be a
worker precisely precisely yeah it's
it's almost the opposite this is where
my dyslexia comes in handy I can just
reverse things back and forth a little
bit yeah
but the the sense yeah it's almost the
opposite the direct opposite of the
sense that you're talking about as the
always already abiding
right disclosed even in its disclose its
undisclosed rights already here
work has this almost the sense of like
as a worker there's always more work and
I am through my work but because I'm a
worker I never get the work done so
there's this yeah I can never be
complete yeah that is the impossibility
that is my burden no matter how nice my
work is yeah so it's almost like an
enactment in a total way of the
forgetfulness of being beautiful it is
it's an ongoing seemingly unending
enactment of the forgetfulness of being
yes
thinking of that and that's why it's so
darn hard this is I'll use the word like
that's why it's so tiring hard to talk
about it many contexts because it
therefore is always ripe for
misinterpretation the key is not to get
the understanding of critique employed
at work that's that's the reenactment
the misinterpretations are part of the
process of continue to stand as the
worker the the continue that the point
is to continue to repudiate the
arguments made about total work in order
to see that of course it's the case that
meaningful work is possible or if of
course it's the case that we have
callings our crews whatever flavor you
want you can always find a way to bend
and swerve and and and usually don't
invent and swerve you just miss
understand you miss misinterpret and
that would suggest that that's part of
what it is to keep keep oneself taking
the stand as the worker
hmm the workers the worker just
analogous to the egit worker like the
ego-self is threatened because you can't
take your stand as the worker and
understand what's being said mmm just
doesn't philosophy you you you feel the
the perfume of being in and through the
philosophizing and just as in philosophy
the understanding is the relaxation so
and when I call public philosophy this
critique of total work in particular you
need to actually take a different stand
in order to understand what's being said
you know I'm ok with it ever since a
humor about it but it's it's a it's a
it's it's frightful and horrifying
mm-hmm because you would see that if you
if you read a number of pieces that try
to summarize what I'm writing
they're they're misunderstandings these
are even supposedly sympathetically
people they're misunderstandings of what
is being said unwittingly in order to
continue being a total worker in some
fashion or another mm-hmm right yes it's
very stinker like yeah yeah yeah like I
oftentimes think about that sense of
like there's there's must have certain
muscles like prime movers that cross a
joint that when it contracts it does
something that then does something else
these muscles that when they contract
the whole thing contracts yes yes yes it
is
and that's wasn't freaking the pre
contraction before the arriving of
so-called arguments about total work the
sphincter tightens in preparation for
transcends itself through its in skunky
nation in the trans and 3
there's another teacher of mine talked
about something he's similar to my dad
we talked about something called the
what he calls the food bird and how he
describes the food bird the food bird
poop is the sound the bird makes as it
flies in ever concentric circles and the
moment it flies up its own ass okay
everyone knows exactly what you mean
when you can hear the sound of the food
burglar in there you know it's funny as
I'm as I'm talking about it there is
there's like it is it the irony right of
of just the response of humor to it
right but at the same time the humor
admits the core the horror of it right
on another level and I think that's one
of the things I've come to appreciate
about Heidegger right is he's you know
in in it there's a there's a tone of
your I feel a tone of what when you talk
about this of a very similar sensibility
of my understanding of what he's talking
about is the inflaming - Todd lysing of
techni City or in in framing of our time
when he says the the famous phrase
desist and in the saving power or within
the danger is the saving power and what
I've come to understand what he's
talking about
is is that the the danger on the one
level is what's happening right
what's happening is that the danger is
how P it's easily a truly dark time is
people walking around going talking
about how dark it is a truly dark time
is everyone's walking around and no
one's not they're not even not noticing
it's not dark and what I'm a pre I get
this I get this kind of ontological
tickles or something as we talk about
total work of entering into seeing the
absurdity seeing the darkness as the
darkness right seeing in it precisely
how uncanny this is a total isin effect
very uncanny yeah can you believe that
we actually live in a society where this
is the case it's it's almost
incomprehensible and even and here's the
thing is no it's and it's possible to
not even comprehend that I'm not
comprehending how weird it is an uncanny
it is and that even is I think reflected
in what you're talking about
in the totalizing sense of social media
right where we get on our screen okay
sometimes I can't this thought
experimental like imagining you know
like I go to sleep it's 1970 and I go to
work every day and I use the BART let's
say and I wake up and it's 2020 but I
don't know it Bart st. Bart station and
I want and and all of a sudden everybody
is staring right at this thing that
they're holding yes in fact everybody on
the things like this look around and
they're dead oldest shovels and then
they're like this what would I think
it's like I think I would think whatever
that is it got us
that's a funny tale on Rip Van Winkle is
a nice lady kind of tweaked tweak'd it
right it's the Rip Van Winkle tale about
falling asleep before the Revolution
waking up afterward but if you fell
asleep and things weren't great but
apparently the part was operating you
woke up afterwards and yeah you're at
work side and you're right it got us
guys in it in what's interesting what's
even even more penny about that I would
say no more but like part of its uncanny
miss is that really only happened in the
last 10 years or so yes right and in
debt that's such a dramatic orientation
and it just happened a fraction of a
second ago and it's completely
disappeared that in itself is like Emily
spooky that's spooky but at least you
have people who just remember what it
was like before cellphones up to the
point yeah what if you can't remember it
was like before the worker became the
ontological stand or stands yeah
[Laughter]
something I can't be if there is a
quality of like touching in it it's like
almost like swallowing metal like
nothing about me is designed for that
it's almost like yes to get it
yes yeah exactly and what's also
unfortunate is that there are these some
symptom all manifestations of it as in
the case of burning to take the one
example or as in the case of thing
overwhelmed to another their own but but
then they're always miss recognized are
almost always miss recognized as a
narrow mental health concern the
w-h-o called burnout and occupational
occupational problem or something like
this you've had the the perpetuation of
total work happens on I'm arguing this
has been helpful today to see this
because I'm arguing through this miss
apprehension misinterpretation yeah it's
it's very easy to say we should have
before we should have a four-day work
week or we should we should go with ubi
or we should we should appeal to labor
movement 19th century it's a very good
movement in 19th century that led to
better labor conditions for people
working in factories and led to the
40-hour workweek the five the five day
work day workweek
I'm sympathetic to that to be sure but
I'm not talking about that any
psychological it's just narrowly
psychological or sociological
interpretation tends to be a
misinterpretation policy statements
always begin from the stance of the
worker right now sixteen point eight
million Americans have recently filed
unemployment and what we're going to do
alas is double down on making them into
more and more choppers we're going to
re-educate them and make them choppers
again I'm going on my high horse but
what I'm trying to say is that the job
er is just one instantiation of the
worker and it's one I think very suspect
and nefarious version the careerist is
another more sophisticated or slightly
more sophisticated ideologically
entrapped version of the worker and the
worst version I think right now is the
one who really called goes in for
something like a calling which is a very
pleasant countenance notion says I have
a calling to work I have a calling to be
a creative class is this person a
knowledge worker yeah I yes I have a
colleague part of the calling
I don't notice that the eye is
completely wedded and given by this this
total work and I call out hi yeah the
late Marxist Willy Alta Sara would talk
about however called into subjective
ation I haven't thought about this model
but you're called forth as the worker
and you don't realize that that was the
call to you you already heard and now
now you've been playing out that role
but it's it's just so fundamentally
untrue to our own direct experience this
is why be before we went into total work
I said I am trying to lift the veil to
change metaphors on anything that is
actually precluding very possibility of
the kind of intimate beautiful heartfelt
searching conversation you and I am
having today I want to put in that very
immediate sense so that there's some
tactfulness so that I'm not just saying
things they're a highfalutin I want to
say it's right here right here's what I
care about
yeah it's it's right here it's possible
it's actualizing itself right now right
and if the question let's say that I or
or someone really got what you're
talking about
like really got it and really and was in
the in the understanding of it how would
they know
because it's there's the because I'm
really I'm just really with this and I
notice as I'm as we're talking about
this I feel myself becoming more and
more and more and more and more spacious
yeah and there's an awareness of this
spacial miss of like if I pull on one of
the threads the whole thing's gonna
happen
right yes and I think this is what
happened he asked us this question is
cuz oh yeah there's a there's something
that you are offering if you will in the
inquiry they that you're that you're
doing that's the kind of understanding
that is distinct from the understanding
from within the frame right and so what
I guess the question is if the
understanding was an understanding that
wasn't pulling on the thing right
how would one know that one was
understanding what's being spoken about
the Bible says there is a peace that
surpasses all understanding that person
would know that peace would know that he
or she is peace itself
hmm and that's different from feeling
kind of a nice sense of transient peace
when the work day is over and before the
next work date begins well it's not the
same as relief or feeling unencumbered
for a moment for chronologically
speaking piece itself is our being
it's you know and so it's so clear has
to be undeniable you can't you can't you
can't this is not a Cartesian moment in
which you you've heard wrong some
certainty through that skeptical method
yeah we haven't rung anything out it's
not the so you've thank goodness we have
some certainty no you just you know it
because it's you you know it because
it's absolutely indubitable you wouldn't
think to doubt it then how do you know
when you're in love with someone for
real
it's tautological you just you know it's
I just love her Montaigne said that it
was late friend friend she was very very
much in love with sense of brotherly
love why why he asks in a very monotone
in spirit why I love my friend because
it was he because it was mmm very
beautiful and very true but completely
propositional II nothing hmm but we but
he's trying to basically describe the
indescribable something he already knows
if I say what I love my wife because it
was she because it is because it is she
because it is
how do we know and we're not in the
throes of total work because we actually
experience peace itself well and or we
go and if you want it's a little bit
matrix or somesuch from you look out at
what people are doing now it no longer
I'm sure this would take some time as it
does in the spiritual practice but it no
longer is it's a grip on you you realize
that this is people are seeing life
through a glass half darkly you you see
it as a language game or a discourse
you're a bit of a routine ironist
whichever version you want but you begun
to see it as something that stands over
and against you but is not your abiding
peace any time you find yourself
contracting into the worker again oh I
see mmm that was the habit this is mmm I
know what kind of contempt is you have
but you know usually this tractions back
into our ordinary forms of
identification but over time through
relaxation through through the depths of
understanding the piece is the piece
becomes where we abide how we abide it
as we abide fighting yeah it is a way
where I would say I feel
sense of just being present there's a
quality of it's almost like as if every
point it was like every if everything
were made of points there
opening at once yeah this is scribe
Islam there's a
there's a
yes there's a tonne through everything
yeah thank you so much you're welcome so
much thank you very much for this
conversation
this is really really I really really
enjoyed I enjoyed it immensely
yeah I'm really beautiful thank you yeah
received fully and now they think I
think the thing I'm appreciating about
it is Rick look actually I'm reading
right now with them and maybe we can
have you on when we when we read a
dialogue with another where there's like
three in a lockers or something but
Chris Chris and I are doing a series
where we just read the Platonic
dialogues oh wow yeah and I'm I'm it's
funny and I've never really read the
dialogues and in reading them I I heart
cannot a number of Asians as we've been
talking to some of the little ginger
experiences that yeah in with Socrates
and there's one of the things I've
really appreciated about it so far is
there's this way where Socrates it's
talking to in the first one that we're
reading czaka bodies right
and he tests but he's just taking out
every single peg right it just almost
like it feels like he's lining up
Domino's they're just utterly not
answering question but undoing the quit
and it's like it's before before and
what's interesting is as the dialog it
is doing its thing
there's this kind of sense in where
World War we're walking around something
that is undefined that in some sense
can't be defined yet is present
right and in all not being able to
answer the questions right yeah that
sense of just circling the sense of
circling around something that a hollow
if you will the hollow becomes a
presence inside
yes yeah I think I just really have the
reading of that and in the style of the
talking about your work and the
experience of what it how one would know
with one understood I'm getting just all
that's missing for me I really
appreciate I think part of what I'm
appreciating about the conversation yeah
oh I just really appreciate the tone in
the conversation I felt as though really
from the beginning we were able to move
into intimacy yeah yeah very a very
beautiful mmm-hmm thank you look nice to
meet you nice to meet you too yes I'm
certainly we'll do this again yeah I
would love that yeah let me just say
something fun in keeping with this
conversation before we before we depart
and that is that I had no idea that you
even wanted to have a conversation today
that would be recorded okay just assumed
we were chatting mm-hmm is an
interesting hmm yeah what's interesting
about it well let's say if it were 10
years ago work 15 years ago that would
have been very surprising to me and it
would have been perhaps a dramatic shift
from the first part which is just you
just you you and I to the so the other
part where there's you I and whoever it
is that will be viewing this
that's just it's just well as moments
for you maybe there's a little pride
speaking but you just picked you realize
your spiritual practices actually it's
it's actually here yeah yeah yes I guess
I don't that since I'm too prideful it's
just oh okay that's good too
that's good that's fine too oh that
we're doing okay you know okay sure I
guess you could say yes and your
improvisation or whatever else was like
there was no difference yeah yeah yeah
it's really sweet
yeah mmm it was really sweet thank you
you're welcome
mmm nice to meet you my friend nice to
meet you too take good care
YouTube